[Music]
Welcome to the 2025 release wave 1.
What's new in financial reporting? This
part is for users of
reports. We're going to talk about four
things that you get. Uh slimmer user
interface, accounting format for
negative numbers, portrait mode for PDF,
and finally uh Excel layouts. So let's
dive into it. In Business Central, you
get to financial reporting from your RO
center in many ways. I just use the
financial reporting link here. And uh
you notice a few things on this page
compared to previous editions. First is
there's now an internal description. You
can see here the income statement has uh
an internal description. This is the
thing we use for audit purposes. And the
prior uh version had a description here.
This is now called display title because
the display title is the one used when
viewing the report and when exporting to
PDF. Let's dive into the income
statement here and just go to the view
mode of the report. The first thing you
notice is that um this title is now a
little bit slimmer or better. Um it has
the the display title of the report that
was before shown here. So that gives a
little bit more space on your screen. If
I hide all the options, um you note that
there is an introductory and a closing
paragraph shown here. This is the report
author that has put in a text like this
is a preliminary edition of the
statement. And uh for closing paragraph,
it's something about the Joe's honest
auditing is is uh auditing this. So
that's something new uh but not
something you really set as a user. It's
just the report author who defines this.
If you want to have this even more slim,
you can use personalization to hide the
row number because this is just coming
from the row definition and maybe we
don't really care about that. So this is
I think as slim as we can get to the
report when you are in view mode. Now
the agenda mentioned something about
account for accounting formats for
negative numbers. So here we just use a
minus sign. But if you show all options,
you can see a new option here, negative
amount format. If I choose instead of
minus sign parenthesis, you can see that
this is then showing minus negative
numbers using that notation. And this is
not only when you view the report. If we
choose export to Excel or print and
print it to um PDF, let's just uh
preview the report here. You notice that
that accounting format is being set
right there. So you can see the the
parentheses here and also you can see
this intro and closing paragraphs on the
page. This um PDF is in portrait sorry
in landscape mode. It's been like that
forever in in this feature. As a new
thing, we also added portrait um mode.
If your report is more geared towards
that towards that, you can get your
report uh showing up like
that. All right. Now, we are here in
export to Excel. Um these two actions
are the the old way of doing uh Excel
templates. So, this is where you get a
template. This is where you upload it
and update it with data. There's a new
thing here in this wave. We added
something we call Excel layouts. So you
notice a new action here, open using
layout. And there's also a new thing
here called default Excel layouts. Now,
how do we set an Excel layout on a
financial report? Well, you go to
definitions and choose this new action
here, Excel
layouts. And um this allows me simply to
say maybe I would want to say my fiscal
fiscal year 25 as my code. And this is
my fiscal uh
2025 Excel template or Excel report for
the
income
statement. I can also choose which file
name I want. Maybe I want fiscal
25 income
statement. Okay. So, um now I'm ready to
export this to Excel and uh this will
just give me a template. You can see the
file name is matching this. Open
this Excel file
here. This is just um the data. So,
typically I would hide this uh and do my
actual report in a different worksheet.
So, let me uh just show you real quick.
Income statement. I'll maybe put this as
a title with
u a larger font. And then I want to
refer to this part or this part of the
report. So, let me just do that. So, uh
let's equal
um this part here. And then I want to
drag this down here. And drag it all the
way down here. Let me just give this a
little bit more space. And finally,
maybe I want to do some
formatting here, here,
um, and maybe my income here. Uh, I want
probably also want to format my zeros.
There are multiple ways you can do that.
Either with conditional formatting or
simply remove the zeros from the
worksheet. But this is not an Excel
video. This is about financial
reporting. I'm sure you can do that.
Finally, I want to just put the income
statement here as my worksheet name. And
I want to hide my data tab here. I don't
need to show this. So, this is this is
our Excel layout. I'll save this for now
and go back to Business Central.
So, back on my financial report Excel
layout page, I will uh import
my Excel workbook here and just open
this. And now it's imported into
Business Central. I can have multiple of
these. So maybe I could also have a
fiscal year 26. That would be a new
version. And uh give that another file
name. And I could upload that as well.
So I can have as many of these as I
want. And I can simply run my Excel
layout
um from directly from here. So in in in
in case I want to do the first one here
and choose export and run, I can do
that. And then I will run the report now
with the recent
data. But in business center, sorry,
sorry, back in uh on financial reporting
page, I might want to pick one of these
as my default layout. So that's what
this default Excel layout is for. And
I'll just choose my fiscal year 25
layout here. And when I do that or when
I have done that, my open in Excel using
layout will choose the default layout.
So now I can simply run my my report
here directly from the page. where I
don't have to upload it again. I can
just have my Excel layout um present in
business central and I can share this
between the users of the
report. That's uh that's it for for the
user part of financial reporting
changes.